<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Known saying in the New Testament, that a kingdom divided can't stand</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 8 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A47583</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12868249</idno>
  <idno type="VID">94765</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2264196338</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing K737</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18018</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">12868249</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A47583)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 94765)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 985:31)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Known saying in the New Testament, that a kingdom divided can't stand</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>14 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London  :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1688?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="topical_term">Dissenters, Religious --  Great Britain.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-02 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>John Latta </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-11 </date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="tract">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:94765:1"/>
            <p>THE known saying in the <hi>New-Testament,</hi> That a <hi>Kingdom divided can't stand,</hi> is very seasonable at this Juncture, by all <hi>Protestants</hi> to be seriously considered: And if ever <hi>Ʋnity</hi> (if not in <hi>Worship,</hi> yet in <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Affections</hi>) will be necessary, it must certainly be <hi>Now;</hi> when the <hi>Common Enemy</hi> is seeking, by all means imagina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, to correct such <hi>Divisions</hi> amongst <hi>Protestants,</hi> as if possible to render them irreconcileable <hi>One</hi> to the <hi>Other.</hi> And though the <hi>Differences</hi> are not extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary; yet it has been the <hi>Policy</hi> of those that delight in the <hi>Division</hi> and <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>struction</hi> of <hi>Hereticks,</hi> (as they call them) to widen the <hi>Breaches,</hi> and, as much as possible, divide the <hi>Interest</hi> of <hi>Protestants.</hi> To effect this <hi>Design,</hi> how often have we heard of the many <hi>Disguises</hi> and <hi>Shapes</hi> they have appeared in, among all sorts of <hi>Protestants</hi> (none excepted); and it is lamentable to think, how great an effect they have had on <hi>Passionate Men,</hi> of all <hi>Perwasions.</hi> But now, considering the circumstances of <hi>Things,</hi> and how darkly they appear to <hi>Judicions</hi> and <hi>discerning Eyes,</hi> it's high time for all <hi>Parties</hi> to lay aside <hi>Pride, Passion,</hi> or <hi>Division;</hi> and, as far as possible, agree to <hi>Love</hi> and <hi>Serve</hi> each <hi>Other.</hi> The doing of which, is the only effectual Means to establish a lasting <hi>Ʋnion</hi> among <hi>Protestants,</hi> and to subvert the <hi>Designs</hi> of <hi>Plotting-Men,</hi> who would gladly over-turn our <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Laws.</hi> The <hi>Considerations</hi> above-mentioned, caused me to give the best <hi>Advice</hi> I could: I must confess, not only my ina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, but also my engagement in Business, very much prevented my <hi>Design:</hi> But however, what I here offer, comes from a sincere <hi>Desire</hi> for allaying the <hi>Heats,</hi> and uniting the <hi>Interests</hi> and <hi>Affections</hi> of <hi>Protestants</hi> in general. I hope, I shall not offer any think contrary to <hi>Reason,</hi> and the <hi>Publick Good</hi> of <hi>Mankind.</hi> I shall begin with the <hi>Church of England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Worthy Sirs,</hi> The former <hi>Passion</hi> and <hi>Violence</hi> of some few <hi>Rash Men</hi> amongst you, together with their <hi>Zeal</hi> to serve an ungrateful sort of <hi>Men,</hi> rendred almost the whole <hi>Body</hi> obnoxious to the hard <hi>Opinion</hi> and <hi>Censure</hi> of many <hi>Worthy Men;</hi> insomuch, that those who were really <hi>Members</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> as by <hi>Law</hi> establish'd were at a stand, and did not know what to think of the strange and unaccountable <hi>Speeches</hi> and <hi>Actions</hi> of many, both <hi>Clergy</hi> and <hi>Laiety:</hi> But, as this Fault can be imputed to but a small part of you, so I have that <hi>Charity</hi> to hope, they are, by this time, fully convinced of their <hi>Error,</hi> and will act more Prudently for the future. The heat of a few <hi>Rash Men</hi> ought not to bring so Venerable a Body of Men into contempt; for by that Rule, the most <hi>Innocent</hi> would be lyable to answer for the most <hi>Guilty;</hi> the Injustice of which, can't be sufficiently declared with Abhorrence.</p>
            <pb n="2" facs="tcp:94765:2"/>
            <p> My humble Advice is; As you have always manifested your <hi>Loyalty</hi> to the <hi>King;</hi> so continue Obedient <hi>Subjects,</hi> as far as the <hi>Laws of God</hi> and the <hi>Land,</hi> warrant your <hi>Obedience,</hi> and no farther are you actively obliged to <hi>Obey;</hi> (as to your <hi>Passive Obedience,</hi> ye are no Strangers to the meaning of it; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, I wave it:) Let your <hi>Obedience</hi> to the <hi>Divine</hi> and <hi>Human Laws,</hi> thereto agreeing, be without the least Hesitation or Reluctancy: But, if any thing be commanded by <hi>Man,</hi> you must always remember your prime <hi>Obedience</hi> is due to <hi>God;</hi> and no <hi>Commands, Threats,</hi> or <hi>Allurements,</hi> ought to Influence you so, as to violate the <hi>Laws of God,</hi> or the <hi>Land;</hi> always have an Eye to the <hi>Divine,</hi> which infinitely supercedes any <hi>Command</hi> or <hi>Human Law.</hi> For In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance, if at any time you are required to renounce your <hi>Sence</hi> and <hi>Reason,</hi> and believe <hi>Transubstantiation,</hi> or to <hi>Worship Images, Invocate Saints</hi> and <hi>Angels,</hi> or any other thing, contrary to <hi>Scripture;</hi> or to change your Holy, Pure, and Sound <hi>Religion,</hi> to embrace another, abounding with <hi>Novelties,</hi> full of <hi>Human Inventions</hi> and <hi>Absurdities;</hi> and that has little or no foundation on <hi>Scripture</hi> or <hi>Reason:</hi> You are not, on any pretence whatsoever, to forsake your <hi>certain Religion,</hi> for the embracing of <hi>One,</hi> not only <hi>dubious</hi> but <hi>dangerous:</hi> And let me assure all wavering <hi>Christians,</hi> (who, for Worldly <hi>Interests</hi> and <hi>Preferments,</hi> care not what <hi>Religion</hi> they are of) That they cannot Answer it to <hi>God,</hi> if they make Shipwrack of a good <hi>Conscience,</hi> by turning from a safe and rational <hi>Religion,</hi> to that which is not only <hi>unreasonable,</hi> but very <hi>ridiculous,</hi> in the judgment of all Good <hi>Christians.</hi> Since the <hi>Protestant Religion</hi> is founded on <hi>Reason</hi> and <hi>Truth,</hi> consonant to the <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi> the practice of the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>postles,</hi> and <hi>Primitive Christians,</hi> in all <hi>Ages;</hi> you, and all that desire to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove themselves sincere <hi>Protestants,</hi> ought to continue stedfast in that <hi>Divine Faith,</hi> you profess your selves <hi>Members</hi> of. If your <hi>Religion</hi> was built only on the <hi>Sandy Foundations</hi> of <hi>Tradition, Infallibility,</hi> &amp;c. you might have some tollerable <hi>Plea</hi> for altering your <hi>Opinion;</hi> but as long as your <hi>Religion</hi> teaches you <hi>Obedience</hi> in all Things to <hi>God,</hi> and likewise to your <hi>Soveraign,</hi> in which you have sound Expositions of the <hi>Divine Truths,</hi> the <hi>Sacraments</hi> duly and truly administred in <hi>both kinds,</hi> according to <hi>Christ</hi>'s <hi>Institution;</hi> the <hi>Scriptures</hi> no ways <hi>Lock'd up</hi> from <hi>Clergy</hi> or <hi>Laiety,</hi> (Because all these, and what-ever more is necessary for the ordering of a <hi>Christian</hi>'s <hi>Conversation,</hi> is to be found in the <hi>Protestant Religion</hi>) I can't conceive, why any one should change his <hi>Profession. Worldly Interests, Troubles,</hi> or <hi>Temptations,</hi> ought to have no sway or force with us, when they come in competition with our <hi>pure Religion.</hi> I have enlarged the more on this <hi>Head,</hi> by reason now is a time of greater tryal than formerly; and that some, who not long since esteemed themselves <hi>Pillars</hi> of the <hi>Protestant Faith,</hi> have now, for sinister Ends, without <hi>Reason,</hi> departed from it. But let them seriously consider, there is a <hi>God</hi> above, who will not be <hi>Mocked.</hi> Such <hi>unstable Souls</hi> I shall leave to that <hi>God,</hi> who judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:94765:2"/>all Men, and rewardeth All according to their <hi>Deeds,</hi> whether <hi>Good</hi> or <hi>Evil.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the next place, Let the <hi>Laws</hi> of the <hi>Land</hi> be your <hi>Rule;</hi> Be sure give no advantage to the <hi>Common Enemy,</hi> either by a partial Execution of them, or by doing less than the <hi>Laws</hi> allow: neither strain them too <hi>high,</hi> nor let them be as a <hi>Cypher,</hi> which will signifie nothing, without the <hi>Figure</hi> of <hi>Execution.</hi> As the publick Good and Welfare of <hi>Mankind,</hi> was the design of all <hi>Laws;</hi> so the Conformity to, and Execution of them, ought to have the same tendency. To strain any <hi>Law</hi> beyond the designed <hi>Good,</hi> or <hi>Intent</hi> of the <hi>Legislators,</hi> is a most severe and unjust <hi>Oppression;</hi> and to <hi>suspend,</hi> or let wholesome and beneficial <hi>Laws</hi> lye <hi>dormant,</hi> without all due Execution for the <hi>Publick Good,</hi> does not only shew the unfaithfulness of the <hi>Magistrate,</hi> to whom the <hi>Exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cutive Power</hi> appertains; but also, how little he minds his <hi>Sworn Duty,</hi> which is to see the <hi>Laws</hi> duly put in <hi>Execution;</hi> and <hi>Justice,</hi> according to them, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qually distributed without <hi>Partiality;</hi> and how any can Answer the <hi>nullifying</hi> them, without a Lawful <hi>Abrogation,</hi> by the same <hi>Power</hi> that <hi>Enacted</hi> them, I can't possibly conceive; for the common approved Maxim is, <hi>That Power, only that made any</hi> Law, <hi>has sufficient Authority to suspend or repeal the same.</hi> The Laws of the <hi>Land,</hi> so long as they are founded on <hi>Reason,</hi> and found beneficial to the <hi>Publick Peace</hi> and <hi>Welfare</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> ought to be kept Inviolable, and maintain'd by All; but more especially by those that have any share in the <hi>Execution</hi> of them. We should reckon him a <hi>Mad-man,</hi> that should <hi>un-tile</hi> his House, under pretence of keeping out the <hi>Rain.</hi> Likewise, if a Governour of a well Fortified City, who wanted for no Accommodations requisite for the defence of it, should, without any just cause of Fear of his Inconsiderable Enemies, either out of <hi>Cowardice</hi> or <hi>Persidiousness,</hi> betray the City, and make himself and them, not only void of <hi>Power,</hi> but in effect <hi>Slaves</hi> to the Will and Pleasures of that part of Men, to whom he and they might have bid defiance. What can we say or think of such <hi>Esau's,</hi> that are ready to sell their <hi>Birth Rights</hi> for a <hi>Mess</hi> of <hi>Pottage,</hi> but that they shall not deserve any <hi>Compassion?</hi> and if they undergo the greatest <hi>Evils,</hi> they will have the just <hi>Reward</hi> they have deservedly Merited. I should not pity any Man, that, under pretence of keeping out <hi>Thieves</hi> and <hi>Robbers,</hi> should open the <hi>Door,</hi> and let them in; wholly trusting to their good <hi>Breeding, Kindness,</hi> and <hi>Honesty;</hi> not in the least believing they would be so <hi>unmannerly,</hi> as not only to secure him, by binding his <hi>Hands</hi> and <hi>Feet</hi> that he could not help him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self, but also Rob him of all that was worth their carrying away; stopping his <hi>Mouth</hi> that he could not complain of his hard <hi>Ʋsage,</hi> or call for any help, to free him out of his miscrable <hi>Condition.</hi> I wish, in the Land of <hi>Ʋtopia,</hi> there were not too many, that would shew the same kindness to those kind Hearted <hi>Christians,</hi> that should divest themselves of the <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Security</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:94765:3"/>the <hi>Law</hi> gives them, and meerly trust to their good <hi>Nature,</hi> for their <hi>Religion,</hi> and all their <hi>Liberties</hi> and <hi>Properties.</hi> Any Man, with whom the Administra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Justice</hi> is Intrusted, or that has the Honour to be Elected a Member of <hi>Parliament,</hi> for the Service of his <hi>King</hi> and <hi>Country;</hi> for such a Man to betray his <hi>Trust,</hi> either by <hi>parting</hi> with those <hi>wholsome Laws,</hi> that long ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience tells us, are absolutely necessary, and most beneficial to the <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon-Wealth;</hi> or by condescending to the unreasonable <hi>Desires</hi> and <hi>Endeavours</hi> of an inconsiderable sort of Men; or by not <hi>obstructing,</hi> but <hi>consenting</hi> to the Enacting of <hi>New Laws,</hi> destructive to the <hi>Common Good;</hi> He is most unworthy of the <hi>Trust</hi> reposed in him, and deserves the severest <hi>Punishment</hi> the <hi>Law</hi> will admit of: No <hi>Contempt, Disgrace,</hi> or <hi>Derision,</hi> can be bad enough for such a Man, that to serve his own particular private <hi>Interest,</hi> will <hi>Sacrifice</hi> the <hi>Publick.</hi> All <hi>Members of Parliament,</hi> when they design to make any <hi>Laws,</hi> ought throughly to consider, what <hi>Good</hi> or <hi>Benefit</hi> will accrue to the <hi>Subjects</hi> thereby; and if, upon mature Consideration, they see a necessity of Enacting such <hi>Laws,</hi> by no means ought they to be <hi>omitted,</hi> or <hi>laid aeside.</hi> On the other side, if former <hi>Parliaments</hi> had, for weighty <hi>Reasons,</hi> made several <hi>Acts</hi> for the security of our <hi>Religion</hi> and <hi>Laws;</hi> before these <hi>Laws</hi> be made void by a <hi>Repeal,</hi> due respect ought to be had to the circumstances of <hi>Things</hi> and <hi>Times;</hi> and, after a strict and impartial Enquiry be made, if it shall appear that the Repealing those <hi>Acts</hi> will not only very much <hi>injure,</hi> but really <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>danger</hi> the <hi>Publick Peace</hi> and <hi>Welfare</hi> of the <hi>Kingdom;</hi> then, notwithstanding the Solicitations of a <hi>Party,</hi> whose <hi>Interests</hi> oblige them to desire it, they ought not to part with <hi>Laws</hi> which will prove as an <hi>impregnable Bulwark</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst our <hi>Enemies.</hi> To make void an useful and necessary <hi>Law,</hi> under a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence of doing <hi>Good</hi> to the <hi>Publick</hi> thereby, is like the taking up of a <hi>Sluce</hi> to <hi>prevent</hi> an <hi>Inundation of Water.</hi> I may rather compare it to the throwing of <hi>Combustible Matter</hi> into an House on <hi>Fire,</hi> thinking thereby to <hi>Extinguish the Flames;</hi> which is so far from putting a period to them, that, on the contrary, it heightens the <hi>Flames,</hi> that they are not (if at all) easily Mastered. I have heard our necessary <hi>Laws</hi> compared to the most useful <hi>Damms</hi> and <hi>Banks</hi> in <hi>Holland,</hi> to prevent the raging <hi>Sea</hi> from over-whelming them. It's well known to <hi>Travellers,</hi> of what a vast Importance those <hi>Defences</hi> are: for, should there be a considerable Breach made in any of those <hi>Damms,</hi> that secure them from the violence of the <hi>Water;</hi> not only many <hi>Souls, Beasts,</hi> and many other <hi>valuable Things</hi> would be lost; but it would be an Immense Charge to repair them: But, though the damage to the <hi>Netherlands</hi> would be very great, should such a bad accident happen; yet it's the Opinion of <hi>Wise men,</hi> (and not without good grounds) that should <hi>English-Men</hi> and <hi>Protestants</hi> part with those <hi>Laws,</hi> that are like a <hi>strong</hi> and <hi>impregnable Defence</hi> to them, and their <hi>Religion,</hi> in <hi>one Respect</hi> it would be of a far worse consequence to
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:94765:3"/>them; that is, the <hi>loss</hi> would be <hi>irrepairable;</hi> and <hi>Ten Thousand</hi> to <hi>One,</hi> if ever the like <hi>Security</hi> can be obtain'd. <hi>Country-men</hi> have an <hi>Old,</hi> but <hi>True saying;</hi> that is, <hi>If you love to be free from a Broken Head, keep fast the Staff in your own hand;</hi> so may you not only prevent your being <hi>beaten</hi> by your <hi>own Weapon,</hi> but, in case of an <hi>Assault,</hi> you may, by being in a posture of <hi>Defence,</hi> easily defend your self from <hi>violent Hands;</hi> whereas on the contrary, a <hi>Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked Man</hi> may easily be <hi>Captivated;</hi> and, whether he will or no, he will be constrain'd to submit to the <hi>Mercy</hi> of his <hi>Insulting Enemy.</hi> It's farther ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>served, That after the <hi>Rich Farmer</hi> has, with much difficulty, gotten a good <hi>Estate,</hi> he remembers how hardly he <hi>Laboured, Toiled,</hi> and <hi>Sweated,</hi> before he brought things to so good an <hi>Issue;</hi> and the calling to mind his former Indefa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tigable Labour, has this effect on him, That since he obtain'd his <hi>Riches</hi> or <hi>Substance</hi> with no small <hi>Care</hi> and <hi>Industry,</hi> he is resolved, because he neither got it easily, nor can he dispence with the want of it, that he will not do like <hi>Prodigal Sons,</hi> who being Born to their <hi>Estates,</hi> and wholly Ignorant of their Parents <hi>Care and Trouble</hi> to provide for them, quickly squander away vast <hi>Fortunes:</hi> but though he may love his Children or Friends with all the real Affections imaginable; yet, says he, <hi>Charity begins at home; I must not make my self a Beggar, and stand to the Courtesie of Children or Friends, for what I shall want to sustain me, so that I may comfortably end those days that remain:</hi> For woful Experience too frequently informs us, <hi>That Children and Friends too soon forget their Duty, and the innumerable Kindnesses of their tender Parents.</hi> Since things are thus, let common Prudence dictate better things to us, than to part with what of right belongs unto us, or to let go that <hi>lawful Security</hi> we have, for all that is dear unto us; and by so doing, we may easily prevent our being made a Prey to our implacable <hi>Enemies,</hi> from whose tender Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, <hi>Good Lord deliver us.</hi> I might much more enlarge on this particular; but, should I proceed to enumerate all the manifest <hi>Dangers</hi> and <hi>Inconveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>encies</hi> that I could easily insist on, I should cry out with the <hi>Poet, Tantae molie erat Romanam condere gentem.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the third place, Let your Zeal for your Holy Religion continue, and let your <hi>Moderation</hi> be seen by your very <hi>Enemies;</hi> and let not the worst of them, have any just cause of laying any <hi>severe</hi> or <hi>unbecoming Actions</hi> to your charge: How will it please your <hi>Enemies,</hi> to see you <hi>differing</hi> and <hi>dividing</hi> your <hi>Interest</hi> and <hi>Affections</hi> with those? That a Worthy, and most Learned Member of your Church, in my hearing, lately Preach'd against excluding, by <hi>Excommunication,</hi> from <hi>Communion</hi> with you, for <hi>indifferent Things,</hi> which may be left <hi>undone</hi> and yet <hi>Salvation</hi> obtained. The reasons he gave for lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving them, were, Because there were <hi>many good Christians among them;</hi> and, because they <hi>protested against the same Errors, believed the same Articles of Faith, and hoped for the same common Salvation by Christ, that you do.</hi> You
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:94765:4"/>can't but be deeply sensible, how many Eyes are fixed on you, and what de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sires your <hi>Enemies</hi> have of seeing you exposed to <hi>Publick Shame</hi> and <hi>Contempt:</hi> Have <hi>Charity</hi> towards all Men, especially to all those of the <hi>Protestant Religion,</hi> that in any tollerable Measure conform to the Rules of it. As for your <hi>Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senting Neighbours,</hi> (like the Reverend Doctors, <hi>T<gap reason="illegible: faint" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll.</hi> and <hi>Ten.</hi>) let your Love and Moderation be so great towards them, as if possible, though you cannot make them satisfied with your Reasons for <hi>Conformity;</hi> yet let your <hi>Christian Charity</hi> and <hi>Affection</hi> to them as <hi>Protestants</hi> and <hi>Members</hi> of the same Body you profess to be, have such an Influence over them, as to expel any Malice or prejudice they might have entertain'd against your Persons; and who knows, but such Methods as these, may have a great Influence towards a far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Conformity. It's my Opinion, (and not without Reason) That the bitter <hi>Invectives</hi> not long since, in and out of the <hi>Pulpit,</hi> created greater and fiercer Enemies against the <hi>Church of England,</hi> than otherwise she would have had; but as this has sometime since ceased, so <hi>Charity</hi> ought to be exercised, in forgeting what was amiss; in hopes the like may never be heard again.</p>
            <p>My Advice to you <hi>Dissenting Protestants,</hi> is, for the most part, the same I gave to the <hi>Church of England:</hi> I need not enlarge any farther on the abso<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lute necessity of <hi>Ʋnity</hi> and <hi>Charity</hi> among <hi>Protestants</hi> at this Season, when it is very manifest, that nothing is more delightful or acceptable to those that hate the <hi>Protestant Interest,</hi> than to see one <hi>Protestant</hi> rending, tearing, and back biting another: It being too apparent, that these <hi>Fishers of Men</hi> delight in <hi>troubled Waters,</hi> knowing it to be the fittest time and opportunity to over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come their <hi>Heretical Enemies,</hi> (for so they call <hi>Protestants</hi>) when their Dissen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions among themselves are greatest. Therefore, I earnestly perswade and entreat you, as you tender the Peace and Welfare of the <hi>Kingdom,</hi> and the establishing your sound <hi>Religion,</hi> to put on a Spirit of <hi>Meekness, Charity,</hi> and <hi>Complyance,</hi> as far as possible, with the <hi>Church of England;</hi> and if you can't receive satisfaction enough from her Learned Members, throughly to <hi>Conform;</hi> yet let not your <hi>Charity</hi> be so narrow, as to have a bad Opinion of those Worthy Men, that are abundantly satisfied with the reasonableness of their <hi>Conformity.</hi> As you desire no harsh Censures be past on you for <hi>Nonconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mity;</hi> so be, sure you avoid reflecting on those Pious Men, that hold it lawful to assent and consent to all the <hi>Articles</hi> of the <hi>Church of England.</hi> If possible, have Peace with all Men, especially with those of the same Houshold of <hi>Faith</hi> you profess. Strongly endeavour to prevent bitter <hi>Invective Speeches</hi> against that Church; which, in all probability, is like to be the only Invincible <hi>Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wark</hi> against <hi>Popery:</hi> And I am the more inclin'd to be an earnest Advocate for the <hi>Church of England,</hi> not only because I have hopes she has laid aside those bitter Things, formerly, with some Truth, laid to her charge; but chiefly because a vast number of her Worthy, and eminently Learned Members,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:94765:4"/>have, with great Learning and Solidity defended our Holy Religion, from the <hi>Heresie, Schism</hi> and <hi>Novelty</hi> falsly charged on it by the <hi>Church of Rome.</hi> All Persons that Study any thing to the purpose, of the Controversie betwixt us and them, must certainly perceive, how admirably they have confuted the unreasonable and unaccountable Doctrines of that pretended Infallible <hi>Church;</hi> clearly proving the <hi>Truth</hi> and <hi>Excellency</hi> of the <hi>Protestant Religion;</hi> and that we are not (as they pretend) beholding to them for it: But evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently making it appear, that the <hi>Protestant Faith</hi> is most ancient, and that its Doctrine is consonant or agreeable to the <hi>Word of God,</hi> and the practice of the <hi>purest Christians,</hi> in the <hi>Primitive Times.</hi> This very consideration alone, is sufficient to clear the Body of that Church from being <hi>Popishly affected.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A second Reason to Love and Esteem them for, is, their firm adhering to the known <hi>Laws</hi> of the Land; for what-ever a few unsound <hi>Members</hi> of her <hi>Communion</hi> have done to the contrary, yet she is not accountable for them; the greatest and most considerable part, having been found very faithful on that account.</p>
            <p>A third Thing, for which you ought to value the <hi>Members</hi> of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> viz. Their stedfast adhering to the Rights of the <hi>People,</hi> and espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially of the <hi>Clergy.</hi> Their <hi>Consciences</hi> have been so just, that notwithstand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Angry Frowns of Majesty have taken hold of them, and that they have, and are likely to suffer very much by it; they rather choose to trust <hi>God</hi> with their Temporal Felicity and Comfort, than sinfully violate those Sacred Oaths they have so Solemnly taken, by betraying (in the least) the Trust reposed in them; notwithstanding the Frowns or Allurements of the greatest Men. This only single Instance of their signal Fidelity to <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man,</hi> ought to have no small sway or Influence with all considering Persons. He that orders his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versation according to the Divine Rule, and faithfully Studies to preserve the just <hi>Rights</hi> and <hi>Lawful Liberties</hi> of Mankind, deservedly Merits the greatest Love and Affection imaginable. But he that makes no Conscience of his Duty to <hi>God,</hi> and designedly makes Ship-wrack of the Lawful Rights and Priviledges of any <hi>Party</hi> or <hi>Society,</hi> and that will Sell his Birth-Right for an inconsiderable Value, deserves not the Name of a Man, or to be admitted into the Society of Mankind. I desire you would imitate the <hi>Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> in all those things for which I justly commend her. In the first place, Follow her Loyalty as far as you can, and not break the Laws of <hi>God</hi> nor <hi>Men,</hi> thereto corresponding. In the second place, Be servent and constant in the Sacred <hi>Religion</hi> you profess your selves Members of. You know, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out doubt, the greatest part of you, the Transcendent Excellency of your <hi>Religion;</hi> and therefore, if any of you should, for Interest or Preferment, turn from <hi>Truth</hi> to <hi>Falshood,</hi> from <hi>Light</hi> to <hi>Darkness,</hi> from a <hi>Sound</hi> to a <hi>Corrupt Religion;</hi> How great and unpardonable would so wilful a Sin be? And, to
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:94765:5"/>speak the Truth, I must do you the Justice to commend you for your firmness in your Holy Profession; in that I have heard few or none, that have either gone over, or been perverted to the Communion of the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> not<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>withstanding the alluring Favours of that Church towards you, and practice of her <hi>Clergy</hi> and <hi>Laiety</hi> to gain Proselytes among you. What I shall say on this Head, is, <hi>Go on, and Prosper;</hi> and, without doubt, the Spirit of Truth will guide and direct you for the best. In the third place, Imitate their Fidelity to the Laws of the Land: You can't, but with admiration, perceive how stedfastly they labour to preserve them, and all the reasonable Rights and Priviledges of the People. As you are Rational Men, professing the <hi>Protestant Religion,</hi> and render the <hi>Publick Good,</hi> let not any uncertain Transitory Interest prevail with you so far, as basely to give up your <hi>Religion,</hi> and the known useful <hi>Laws</hi> of the Land; be sure you neither consent to the suspending or taking away any, that (to all Intelligent Men) are like to prove your only Security. When the <hi>Country-man</hi> designs to preserve his <hi>Grain,</hi> from those Creatures that would Eat it up, or otherwise spoil it, he is far from rooting up the Fence that secures it: So ought you carefully to preserve the Laws, for your own and the Publick Safety. Things at present look, to you perhaps, with a good Aspect: I wish, they may long continue in that condition: But, if the course of things should mightily alter, and these <hi>Halcion Days</hi> (of which you have no assurance) should not long continue, how greatly would your hopeful expectations be frustrated? Therefore, be sure you do not impru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently purchase your present Liberty, and seeming Favours, at too dear a rate; for such Acts may wholly deprive you of the Favours, that you may o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwise expect from the next Successor, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But strenuously endeavour to manifest to the World, that your former great out cries against the least In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vasions of your <hi>Religion, Liberties, Properties,</hi> and the <hi>Laws</hi> of the Land, were really in earnest; and, that as then you truly hated those that were in any mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sure guilty of them; so now, it something lyes in your Power, you will not by the greatest Perswasions and Promises of Kindnesses, be wrought on, to part with the <hi>Laws</hi> of the Land, because you can't well be Ignorant of the fatal consequence of so doing. If you either give us the Laws, or cease to execute those that are most necessary, you not only highly serve and gratifie your known <hi>Enemies;</hi> but by betraying your <hi>Trust</hi> you will render yourselves extraordinary Odiour in the Opinion of most Men; in that you are unfaith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to what you formerly so much cryed up, <hi>viz.</hi> That the <hi>Laws</hi> might flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rish, and <hi>Justice</hi> might duly and impartially be distributed, and all Men qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>etly possess what of right belongs to them. No Honest <hi>Man,</hi> or good <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian,</hi> will disswade you from Serving or Obeying your Soveraign, as far as is Lawful: But, in all Obedience, strict recourse must be had to the Divine and Human <hi>Laws,</hi> that the Limits, of neither be Transgressed; and then the
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:94765:5"/>Issue of such Obedience, will be of no ill consequence to you or the Publick; Such Obedience will redound to your Immortal Honour.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> Consider, if the the <hi>Papists</hi> in <hi>England</hi> were not of a rigid, violent, and ambitious Nature, they would not make all this stir about the <hi>Test,</hi> which debars them from a share in the Government. In <hi>Holland</hi> we know, that though the <hi>Papists</hi> are very Peaceable, and have given many Years Testimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies of their good Behaviour, under a <hi>Protestant</hi> Power; yet the <hi>States,</hi> for their own and the Publick Safety, will admit none of them into any <hi>Offices.</hi> I am of Opinion, and not without Reason, <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> here, can't give so good an account of their Peaceable and Christian Behaviour, as those in <hi>Holland</hi> can: Therefore, greater Arguments may be produced, why no Power ought to be granted to them in <hi>England:</hi> It being notoriously known, that though their Prince be a Just Man, valluing his Word, yet a restless Zeal moves the <hi>Papists (manibus pedibusque)</hi> to advance what they call <hi>Catholick Interest;</hi> which, without any Restraint, will not keep within the bounds of Moderation.</p>
            <p>But if the <hi>Laws</hi> are taken off, I know not of any Obstruction they can meet with; then we must expect to be <hi>Govern'd wholly by Papists,</hi> and the conse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence of such a Government must be terrible to <hi>Protestants;</hi> for what can they expect less than <hi>Popish Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons;</hi> and from such a <hi>Parliament,</hi> what less than a perfect establishing of <hi>Popery</hi> by a <hi>Law;</hi> and, without doubt, when such <hi>Laws</hi> are Enacted in favour of that <hi>Religion,</hi> as severe will be made against the <hi>growing of Protestant Heresie</hi> in <hi>England,</hi> from such <hi>Laws,</hi> and such <hi>Times, God</hi> in Mercy deliver <hi>England.</hi> Pray, therefore, consider, if you once give the <hi>Papists</hi> so much Power, whether, so soon as they have it, they will not make severer <hi>Tests</hi> against <hi>Protestants,</hi> than ever were made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the <hi>Church of Rome?</hi> The late Famous Actions of the <hi>French</hi> King, and the <hi>Marian</hi> Kindness of old, to <hi>Hereticks,</hi> are convincing Evidences of the Lenity and Moderation of a Government, wholly in the hands of <hi>Papists.</hi> As for the Happiness, and flourishing of Kingdoms or Republicks, under the <hi>Papists,</hi> See the contrary in Dr. <hi>Burnet</hi>'s <hi>Travels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Romanist</hi>'s great Ambition, and eager desire to be in Eminent Places of Trust, is enough to convince any Rational Man, that for no mean or inconsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derable Enterprises, do they contend for them: They think if once they can get into the <hi>Saddle,</hi> with greater ease they may Ride the poor <hi>Hereticks.</hi> I would advise you to Ponder, with great deliberation, the <hi>Natures, Disposi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions,</hi> and especially the <hi>Interests</hi> of those Men, that with might and main la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to take off the <hi>Test:</hi> And if it shall appear, (as doubtless it will) 'tis a grievance to those only, that espouse a Forreign Interest, directly contrary to yours; and that the <hi>Test</hi> is a strong defence to preserve you. I hope you will manifest your real Love and Kindness to this Nation, by undergoing, for a time, as great Severities as ever, rather than in any degree be Instrumental
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:94765:6"/>in ruining of this now happy Kingdom (I mean in her <hi>Laws</hi>). I would gladly know of any Ambitious <hi>Papist,</hi> Whether it would not be more unreasonably bold for him to desire a share in that Government, from which he is Legally excluded, than for a <hi>Hugonet</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> where, as I never heard, were any <hi>Laws</hi> to exclude him, to desire to be prefer'd to no small Offices: I am ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily perswaded the Body of the <hi>Papists</hi> there, would be very unwilling to be Govern'd by him; I think the case is not parrellel, and that the <hi>Protestants</hi> ought to insist much more on the same Priviledge in <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the <hi>Fifth</hi> place, Seriously think of the professed Kindness of your new Friends of the <hi>Church of Rome,</hi> you may and ought to consider, <hi>Cui bono, For what good or design,</hi> is so great Friendship pretended, and so many Favours now on a suddain confer'd and accumulated on you; who, not long since, were esteemed unworhy of Life: You may well enquire, what occasioned so great a <hi>Calm,</hi> after so violent and <hi>Tempestuous a Storm.</hi> It must, certainly, be matter of the highest admiration to you, to see the wonderful Moderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Clemency of the <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> at this time to you obstinate <hi>He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reticks;</hi> especially since the Members of that <hi>Church</hi> are now in so great Power: I say, to see a <hi>Church,</hi> whose Principles are directly opposite to the <hi>Protestant Interest,</hi> so caress the <hi>strictest sort of them;</hi> when as, not long since, the greatest Violence and Cruelty imaginable, to extirpate them, was thought not only lawful, but necessary; it's well if you find these Kindnesses real, and not to make you, what you hate to be, <hi>Tools</hi> for a Design both dangerous and dishonourable: To see Men, one while, breath out nothing but <hi>Invectives</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the <hi>Reformed;</hi> at another time, if it more serves their purposes, fawn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and courting <hi>Hereticks,</hi> is enough to put considering Men on their Guard. Such unexpected Kindnesses may put you on enquiry.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> Whether you come nearer in Belief or Practice to that <hi>Church</hi> now? or, whether you be as guilty of <hi>Heresie</hi> (as she calls it) as ever?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Whether the usual Spirit of Persecution, and Antipathy to <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants</hi> (though at present in <hi>England</hi> restrain'd) be not as predominant in <hi>France,</hi> and other places, as ever? It's well if <hi>Roman Catholicks</hi> can Act con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to their known and beloved Principles, in puting on a Moderation and Temper suitable to the <hi>Gospel.</hi> If it be clearly evinced, that <hi>Protestant Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senters</hi> have not in the least obliged the <hi>Papists,</hi> by their receeding or depart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from their own Principles; or by their favourable construction of the Articles and Opinions of the <hi>Church of Rome;</hi> then it is visible their designs are (since the <hi>Church of England</hi> will not serve their turn) if possible, to make the <hi>Dissenters</hi> their <hi>Tools,</hi> they being the last Refuge they can fly to, in order to their Assistance. The late Actions of the <hi>Papists,</hi> towards you, bespeak your favourable Opinion: But the too well known Maxim amongst the <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manists, That Faith is not to be kept with Hereticks,</hi> doth justly cause <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:94765:6"/>to expect no real or greater Kindnesses from them, than consists with their <hi>Interests</hi> or <hi>Designs</hi> to manifest. If the <hi>Papists</hi> shew you outwardly great Respect; and, for Sinister Ends, treat you as Friends for a while, till you have served their turn, by taking off the <hi>Test</hi> and <hi>Penal Laws,</hi> that they might be on as equal Terms as you: It's not only <hi>Mine,</hi> but the Opinion of <hi>Ten Thousand</hi> more; that not only you, but the Nation will dearly pay for the Kindnesses you have received from them: And, let me tell you, if things are so ordered, you may Whistle for any place of Trust in the <hi>Government:</hi> And when all the Administration of <hi>Justice</hi> is wholly in the <hi>Romanists</hi> (as doubtless then it will be) you <hi>Hereticks</hi> must be content with such as can be got: For I know not where you can expect any Redress, or to whom you can appeal. These Considerations, I hope, will make you perceive as great a necessity of continuing those <hi>Laws,</hi> as ever there were of Enacting them; especially the <hi>Test.</hi> Pray <hi>God</hi> direct you, that you may act Prudently, for your own Credit, and the Nations Good. I have great cause to hope well of you, because, for the most part, you are Men of Consideration and Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding, that scorn to be Accessaries, much less the chief Actors, in sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verting the happy Constitution of our Government.</p>
            <p>I make no question but your wise Carriage, at this time, by being faithful to your <hi>King,</hi> your <hi>Religion,</hi> and the <hi>Laws,</hi> will so far reconcile you to the favour of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> that when ever a seasonable Opportunity shall offer for the easing of you in a Legal way, her Members will readily consent to it; for they will not be so void of all Gratitude, as wholly to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get your firmness to your Religion, and the necessary Laws of the Land; but if you Act contrary to the Interest of <hi>Protestants,</hi> and of the Nation, you can expect only the short Favours of the <hi>Church of Rome;</hi> and not easily to be admitted into the favourable Opinion of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> nor re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive those Kindnesses from her, which otherwise you might expect. And I must profess, you will deserve none of her Favours, if you study more to serve the <hi>Roman,</hi> than the <hi>Protestant Interest:</hi> But I hope better things of you.</p>
            <p>I shall not enlarge, having (I hope) writ enough to have convinc'd you already. I shall Answer one grand <hi>Objection,</hi> relating to the <hi>Penal Laws;</hi> The <hi>Test</hi> (as I can understand) being not much Insisted on; unless by some Mercenary Men, whose Writings are all they have to depend on. The po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pular Argument, for a present Repeal, with some timerous and passionate <hi>Dissenters,</hi> is this, That the Members of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> are of a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secuting Spirit; and as one, the other end of the City, said, <hi>That while these Rods</hi> (meaning the <hi>Penal Laws</hi>) <hi>are in their hands, they will be continually lashing</hi> Protestants: Therefore, it is (as he said) the highest piece of Pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence to take them off, while it is in their Power. I always heard a great account of the Gentleman, that his Memory was very good, his Parts very
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:94765:7"/>eminent: If so, I can't but admire he forgets, or at least understands not, from whence those severe Orders, for ruining <hi>Dissenters,</hi> came: Nay, farther, for what Ends and Designs things were so violently carried on. Perhaps it may farther be Objected, That many of the Divines of the <hi>Church of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> often Zealously pressed this Persecution. I'll grant the Accusation in part; but I can the better excuse those hot Men, when I consider what <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives, Incentives, and Promotions came from that end of the City, that now so much condemns the Church of</hi> England <hi>for her Zeal to Serve the King in that particular:</hi> Since things were so carried, that no <hi>Clergy-Men</hi> were esteemed or preferred unless he would comply with <hi>Courtly Orders,</hi> in <hi>Thundring</hi> against <hi>Dissenters.</hi> As there are, amongst Men of all Perswasions, Ambitious, Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gent Men; so, I confess, there were some few such as Mr. <hi>Thompson</hi> of <hi>Bristol,</hi> among the <hi>Church of England</hi> Divines: But for the Richer and more Learned part of that vast Body, I am fully convinc'd, few, if any, were of that Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>secuting Spirit. Farther, The Worthy Members of the Church of <hi>England</hi> are grateful Understanding Men; and I have that Charity for them, as not to imagine, That if the <hi>Dissenters</hi> be, to their Power, Friendly and Service<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the Church of <hi>England</hi> now; if it should ever lye in her Members Power hereafter, but that a trebble return of Kindness and Gratitude would by them be made.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Lastly,</hi> To conclude, I must profess, that I hate a Persecuting Spirit in Men, pretending to Christianity; and I do freely declare, I should heartily rejoyce, if this time were a fit opportunity to relieve the <hi>Dissenters;</hi> but, were I in their condition, as I had already undergone much, so, by the Assi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance of <hi>God,</hi> I would Suffer much more, rather than, like <hi>Sumpson,</hi> who, when he had lost part of his Strength, for Revenge, with what he had left, pull'd down the House, not only on the <hi>Philistines,</hi> but on his own Head. Such a Foolish Revenge would be but a poor satisfaction to a Rational Man: How aptly the comparison is made, I leave to understanding <hi>Dissen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> to consider.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <pb n="13" facs="tcp:94765:7"/>
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I</hi> Had almost forgot Two weighty Considerations; The first is, You ought to consider, and seriously reflect on Courtly Favours and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mises; and how the Court opposed the Kindnesses design'd for you by the <hi>Westminster</hi> Parliament: I must acquaint you, That Three Parts in Four, of that Parliament, were strict <hi>Church of England-Men;</hi> and that they had such a respect for you, that they unanimously passed a <hi>Bill</hi> for easing of <hi>Protestant Dissenters;</hi> And I can't conceive, why it was by the Court obstructed, unless because it did not extend to the <hi>Papists,</hi> as well as <hi>Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senters:</hi> However, for Reasons best known to themselves, instead of Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>senting the <hi>Bill</hi> to King <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, to have his Royal Stamp, it was lost (a thing never heard of before): This Act will sufficiently clear the major part of the <hi>Church of England,</hi> from that Odious Accusation of being Promoters of that Persecution, then so vigorously carried on: And since it clears them, it must fall heavy somewhere: I do not affirm, the <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pists</hi> had any hand in losing that <hi>Bill;</hi> but I know not what to think of it. No Man can doubt, but that great Kindness to <hi>Protestant Dissenters,</hi> was really by that Parliament designed: But there was a considerable Party then in being, with whose Interests, Designs, and Glory, such Lenity could not then consist, what ever it may do now.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Some great Advocates for Repealing the <hi>Test,</hi> pretend to an Expedient for it; and declare, they will part with it, provided such Secu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity as can be proposed, may be gotten: As an Expedients, in another Case, was thought Odious and Ridiculous; so now, a <hi>Nominal,</hi> and not a <hi>Virtual</hi> Obligatory Law, ought to have the same Fate. It's my Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, If the pretended Expedient be as Valid and Secure to <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stants</hi> as the <hi>Test,</hi> it would be equally indifferent for the <hi>Papists</hi> to let you keep what you have: And some think, if you must have a <hi>Test,</hi> it will not be grateful to the <hi>Roman Catholicks.</hi> Wherein lyeth the Kindness
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:94765:8"/>of the King, if he parts with any Law, and at the same time grants ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther as severe, to Exclude his Subjects, (whom He thinks Worthy) from all publick Places of <hi>Trust.</hi> I must freely tell you my Mind, If you are concern'd for preserving your Religion, and what is dear to you, and us All, Remember, and abide by that common Proverb, <hi>One Bird in Hand, is worth Two in the Bush.</hi> You would reckon a Purchaser (though he were sure of a Penniworth) very imprudent, if he should Pay the full Value for his Land, before he were sure to receive a satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factory Title from the Vender. As to the Promoters and Patriots of an Expedient, in lieu of the <hi>Test,</hi> In the first place, are they sure such a thing will be granted? I put the <hi>Quaery,</hi> because, of I am not mis-in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed, the <hi>Draconical</hi> Author had no Thanks for proposing it, in his An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer to the <hi>Letter to a Dissenter.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To Conclude, I shall give you my Sentiments in a plain Intelligible In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stance: I can as soon be wrought upon to believe an Ignorant Pretender, that shall pretend to take out my Sound Teeth, and put in a better Sett in the room of them, as to Credit the Promoters of an Expedient: As I should admire at the Confidence of the former, so I should be amazed at the Ignorance of the latter. I believe the impossibility of my getting new sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stantial Teeth, and their getting as firm Security for the <hi>Protestant Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion,</hi> in place of the <hi>Test,</hi> will be alike equal: Therefore, be Prudent, and consider the danger of altering a well-Establish'd Government: For, it's manifest, when things are in Confusion, it's a hard matter to set them right again.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:94765:8"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>